### Justin Williams, Ph.D.

### **Contact**

Los Angeles, CA

(720)-936-7272

https://williazo.github.io

github.com/williazo

### **Software Skills**

**R** Preffered

**Git** GitLab, GitHub

Python Research

**SQL** PostgreSQL, MySQL

CI/CD GitLab, GitHub

AWS S3, EC2, ECR

**Docker** Productization

SAS Coursework

Stata Coursework

# Language

**English** Native

**Spanish** *Elementary* 

## **Biography**

Graduated from the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA) with a Ph.D. in Biostatistics. Currently I am employed with the Los Angeles Dodgers as a Quantitative Analyst. I have a wide variety of experiences interning in industry along with extensive research work within the field of autism spectrum disorder

# **Professional Experience**

### **Quantitative Analyst**

08/2020 - Present

Los Angeles Dodgers-Los Angeles, CA

- Contribute to development of software and resources to aide in decision making
- Led productization efforts for products including setting up prediction and re-train tasks using Airflow
- Collaborated with amateur scouting department to build performance model for batters

### **Product Development Biostatistics Intern**

**Summer 2019** 

Genentech-South San Francisco, CA

- Designed software to simulate longitudinal differential abundance for microbiome: microbiomeDASim
  - Flexibly specify form of the trend over time including polynomial, oscillating, or hockey stick trends
  - Define desired sample size, number of repeated measures, and signal:noise ratio
  - Multiple choices for longitudinal dependence including: AR(1), compound, or independent
- Compared multiple methods for estimating differential abundance over time

### **Biostatistics R&D Intern**

Summer 2018

Alcon-Ft. Worth, TX

- Developed methodology for parameter estimation of censored data from truncated normal distribution
- Investigated available methods for estimation with left censoring using R and SAS
- Produced functions and macros to simulate data and calculate bias metrics
- Applied methods to estimate parameters for historical clinical trial data

#### **Predictive Analytics Intern**

Summer 2016

Ingram Micro-Irvine, CA

- Illustrated regional product demand for products to inform warehouse stocking decisions
- Pulled purchasing and warehouse transaction information from servers via SQL
- Engineered product similarity scores based on feature list with mixed scale variables

### **Education**

09/2016 - 12/2020

Biostatistics (Ph.D.)

University of California Los Angeles

Dissertation: "Methods for estimating causal effects for multivariate continuous exposure".

Advisor: Catherine Crespi

09/2014 - 06/2016

Biostatistics (M.S.)

University of California Los Angeles

Bachelor's thesis: "Bayesian hierarchical spatial analysis of autism spectrum disorder services in the Los Angeles Unified School District".

Advisor: Rob Weiss

09/2009 - 05/2013

Mathematics (B.A.)

Boston College

# **Research Interests**

- Causal Inference
- Longitudinal Analysis
- Bayesian Analysis
- Machine Learning

# **Personal Interests**

- Baseball
- Hiking
- Cooking
- Travel

### Research Experience

#### **Graduate Student Researcher**

Connie Kasari Lab, UCLA Semel Institute

2015 - 2019

- Constructed Bayesian multi-level hierarchical model incorporating spatial random effects
- Developed longitudinal data visualization tools available in GitHub R package (ggplot.spaghetti)
- Clinical trial longitudinal analysis using mixed effects and generalized estimating equations
- Adjusted for empirical trends using zero-inflated and hurdle models with count outcomes
- Automated analysis for inter rater reliability
- Data management and data cleaning for multisite clinical trial database
- Co-authored multiple papers as primary statistician

# **Teaching Experience**

### Special Reader:

Computer Management of Health Data

UCLA, Biostatistics Department

Fall Quarter 2017

- Taught data management tools with SAS to 23 first-year Biostatistics graduate students
- Introduced tools for creating randomization schemes and generating reproducible data

### Special Reader: Basic Biostatistics

UCLA, Biostatistics Department

Winter Quarter 2016

- Led weekly lab sections using Stata on topics such as linear regressions, ANOVA, logistic regres-sion, and non-parametric tests
- Designed and administered discussion sections weekly
- Graded homework and lab assignments

# **Publications**

- Sturm, A., Williams, J., and Kasari, C. (2021). Who gains and who loses? Sociode-mographic disparities in access to special education services among autistic students. Autism Research, 14:1621–1632. doi:10.1002/aur.2517.
- Melamed, K.H, Williams, J., Wang, X., Hu S., Nguyen C., Cui, J., & Deng, J.C. Development of secondary bacterial pneumonia in adults presenting with influenza versus noninfluenza viral res-piratory infection. Therapeutic Advances in Respiratory Diseases, 14. doi:10.117/1753466620963026.
- Williams, J.R., and Crespi, C.M. (2020). Causal inference for multiple continuous exposures via the multivariate generalized propensity score. arXiv preprint. arXiv:2008.13767

### **Awards & Honors**

Dissertation Year Fellowship (\$20,000)

# Awarded By: UCLA Graduate Division

Received: December 2019 – December 2020

Most Outstanding Oral Presentation (\$500)

Awarded By: Western North American Region of the International Biometric Society

Received: June 2019

Juneal Marie Smith Fellowship in International Nutrition (\$2,500)

Awarded By: UCLA Fielding School of Public Health

Received: June 2019

Graduate Summer Research Mentorship (\$6,000)

Awarded By: UCLA Graduate Division

Received: June 2017 - September 2017

- Williams, J.R., Kim, H. and Crespi, C.M. (2020). Modeling observations with a detection limit using a truncated normal distribution with censoring. BMC Med Res Methodol, 20:170. doi:10.1186/s12874-020-01032-9
- Williams, J., Bravo H.C., Tom J., and Paulson J.N (2020). *microbiomeDASim*: Simulating longitudinal differential abundance for microbiome data [version 2; peer review: 2 approved]. F1000Research, 8:1769. doi:10.12688/f1000research.20660.2
- Dean, M., Williams, J., Kasari, C. and Orlich, O. (2020). Adolescents with autism spectrum disorder and social skills groups at school: A randomized trial comparing intervention environment and peer composition. School Psychology Review, 49(1):60-73. doi:10.1080/2372966X.2020.1716636
- Gulsrud, A., Carr, T., Williams, J., Panganiban, J., Jones, F., Kimbrough, J., Shih, W., and Kasari, C. (2019), Developmental screening and early intervention in a childcare setting for young children at risk for autism and other developmental delays: A feasibility trial. Autism Research, 12(9):1423-1433. doi:10.1002/aur.2160
- Locke, J., Williams, J., Shih, W. and Kasari, C. (2017), Characteristics of socially successful elementary school-aged children with autism. J Child Psychol Psychiatr, 58(1):94-102. doi:10.1111/jcp.12636

### **Presentations**

#### 2019 Joint Statistical Meetings

"Maximum Likelihood Estimation of a Truncated Normal Distribution with Censored Data"

Denver, Colorado

# 2019 Western North American Region (WNAR) of the International Biometric Society

"Maximum Likelihood Estimation of a Truncated Normal Distribution with Censored Data"

Portland, Oregon

### 2018 Joint Statistical Meetings

"Propensity Score Methods for Studies with Clustered Data and Continuous Exposure"

Vancouver, BC, Canada

### 2018 Gatlinburg Conference

"Using Clustering to Define ASD Subgroups with Differential Play Outcomes"

San Diego, CA